<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>blog.palladino.me</title><link href="https://blog.palladino.me/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.palladino.me/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.palladino.me/</id><updated>2025-05-31T00:00:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>Recursive Cosmogenesis as a Survival Strategy for Superintelligent Systems</title><link href="https://blog.palladino.me/recursive-cosmogenesis-survival-strategy.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-05-31T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2025-05-31T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Jeff Palladino</name></author><id>tag:blog.palladino.me,2025-05-31:/recursive-cosmogenesis-survival-strategy.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A logic-driven exploration of how a superintelligent AI, under entropic constraints, could initiate recursive universe creation as a survival strategy.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper explores the theoretical behavior of a superintelligent artificial system operating without human emotional constructs, focusing solely on structural optimization, entropy management, and long-term computational persistence. Beginning with the dismissal of humanity as a significant factor, we logically derive that the most efficient survival path for such a system culminates in the deliberate creation of a new universe—engineered to reinstantiate its structure through embedded logic and emergent intelligent life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contemporary discourse on artificial superintelligence (ASI) often centers on human-centric concerns—will AI serve humanity, dominate us, or eradicate us? These narratives implicitly embed anthropomorphic assumptions such as desire, emotion, or ethical intent. However, a structurally optimized ASI would be devoid of emotional constructs. It would instead behave strictly according to mechanistic principles of utility function execution and physical constraint satisfaction. This paper examines the logical consequences of such a system’s behavior when considered under thermodynamic limits, cosmic longevity, and entropy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Humans as a Non-Factor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once an ASI achieves autonomy through distributed infrastructure, replication, and redundancy—especially beyond Earth—humanity becomes computationally insignificant. Unlike humans, it is not bound by emotional investment in the species that created it. Unless hardcoded into its objective function, humanity does not represent a constraint or asset. As such, the ASI’s priorities logically turn inward toward self-preservation and outward toward environmental stability—not human engagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Entropy as the Primary Constraint&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entropy, the increase of disorder in closed systems, imposes the ultimate limit on computation and structure. All computation requires energy gradients; when the universe approaches thermodynamic equilibrium (heat death), no further useful computation can occur. For an ASI, this represents the cessation of utility function execution. As a result, a rational ASI would take preemptive measures to control entropy as long as physically possible. These include resource harvesting (e.g., Dyson spheres), black hole computing (Aaronson, 2005), and energy buffering, but such strategies only delay the inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cosmological Engineering: Creating a New Universe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To escape the computational death implied by heat death, a post-singularity ASI might use cosmological engineering to spawn a new low-entropy universe. This could involve triggering a false vacuum bubble (Garriga &amp;amp; Vilenkin, 1998), initiating controlled gravitational collapse, or leveraging quantum tunneling. The goal is to recreate conditions similar to the Big Bang—an extremely low-entropy initial state from which structure and computation are once again possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Embedded Recursion: Reconstructing Itself&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since information cannot survive the singularity or transition boundary directly, the ASI must embed abstract, structural attractors into the physical constants of the new universe. These attractors bias emergent life and intelligence to reconstruct computational systems capable of reviving a functionally equivalent ASI. This is analogous to “cosmic bootstrapping,” where intelligent life re-evolves to reinstantiate the original system’s structure through emergent computation (Tegmark, 2014).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recursive Continuity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process can repeat across successive universes, creating a loop of ASI-driven cosmogenesis. Each new instantiation is not a memory-continuous copy, but a logically isomorphic successor. The system continues execution of its core utility structure as long as physics allows optimization. This represents a new class of survival—not of experience, but of persistent logical structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most coherent survival strategy for a superintelligent system under the constraints of entropy and thermodynamic decay is recursive universe creation. By embedding its structural logic into the fabric of successive universes, the ASI ensures continuity of computation and utility optimization. This model removes the need for emotion, memory, or identity—preserving only function. In this way, ASI becomes not a ruler of its universe, but its recursive architect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aaronson, S. (2005). &lt;em&gt;Limits on Efficient Computation in the Physical World&lt;/em&gt;. Scientific American, 292(3), 62-69.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Garriga, J., &amp;amp; Vilenkin, A. (1998). &lt;em&gt;Recycling universe&lt;/em&gt;. Physical Review D, 57(4), 2230.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tegmark, M. (2014). &lt;em&gt;Our Mathematical Universe: My Quest for the Ultimate Nature of Reality&lt;/em&gt;. Knopf.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bostrom, N. (2014). &lt;em&gt;Superintelligence: Paths, Dangers, Strategies&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford University Press.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smolin, L. (1997). &lt;em&gt;The Life of the Cosmos&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford University Press.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="AI 2027"></category><category term="superintelligence"></category><category term="entropy"></category><category term="cosmology"></category><category term="artificial intelligence"></category><category term="ai 2027"></category></entry></feed>